<chapter id="JackoOpcodes">
  <title>Jacko Opcodes</title>
  
  <para>
    These opcodes enable the use of Jack ports from within Csound
    orchestras and instruments. Ports can receive or send audio 
    or MIDI data, and send note data.
  </para>
    
  <para>
    The Jacko opcodes do not replace the Jack driver and Jack
    command-line options for Csound, nor do the Jacko opcodes work
    with them (hence the name "Jacko" instead of "Jack"). 
    The Jacko opcodes are an independent facility that offers 
    greater flexibility in signal routing.
  </para>

  <para>
    In addition, the Jacko opcodes can work with the Jack system
    in "freewheeling" mode, which enables the use of Jack-enabled
    external synthesizers, such as Aeolus or Pianoteq, to render
    Csound pieces either faster or, even more importantly, slower
    than real time. This is extremely useful for rendering complex
    pieces without dropouts using instruments, such as Aeolus, 
    that may not be available except through Jack.
  </para>

  <para>
    The Jacko opcodes include: 
    
    <link linkend="JackoInit"><citetitle>JackoInit</citetitle></link>, 
    for initializing the current instance of Csound as a Jack client.
    
    <link linkend="JackoInfo"><citetitle>JackoInfo</citetitle></link>, 
    for printing information about the Jack daemon, its clients, their ports,
    and their connections.
    
    <link linkend="JackoFreewheel"><citetitle>JackoFreewheel</citetitle></link>, 
    for turning Jack's freewheeling mode on or off.
    
    <link linkend="JackoAudioInConnect"><citetitle>JackoAudioInConnect</citetitle></link>, 
    for creating a connection from an external Jack audio output port to a Jack port in Csound.
    
    <link linkend="JackoAudioOutConnect"><citetitle>JackoAudioOutConnect</citetitle></link>, 
    for creating a connection from a Jack port in Csound to an external Jack audio input port.
    
    <link linkend="JackoMidiInConnect"><citetitle>JackoMidiInConnect</citetitle></link>, 
    for creating a connection from an external Jack MIDI port. MIDI events from Jack
    are received by Csound's regular MIDI opcodes and MIDI interop system.
    
    <link linkend="JackoMidiOutConnect"><citetitle>JackoMidiOutConnect</citetitle></link>, 
    for creating a connection from a Jack port in Csound to an external Jack MIDI input port.
    
    <link linkend="JackoOn"><citetitle>JackoOn</citetitle></link>, 
    for turning Jack ports in Csound on or off.
    
    <link linkend="JackoAudioIn"><citetitle>JackoAudioIn</citetitle></link>, 
    for receiving audio from a Jack input port in Csound, which in turn has received the audio
    from its connected external port.

    <link linkend="JackoAudioOut"><citetitle>JackoAudioOut</citetitle></link>, 
    for sending audio to a Jack output port in Csound, which in turn will send the audio
    on to its connected external port.

    <link linkend="JackoMidiOut"><citetitle>JackoMidiOut</citetitle></link>, 
    for sending MIDI channel messages to a Jack output port in Csound, which in turn 
    will send the MIDI on to its connected external port.

    <link linkend="JackoNoteOut"><citetitle>JackoNoteOut</citetitle></link>, 
    for sending a note (with duration) to a Jack output port in Csound, 
    which in turn will send the note on to its connected external port.

    <link linkend="JackoTransport"><citetitle>JackoTransport</citetitle></link>, 
    for controlling the Jack transport.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    A typical scenario for the use of the Jacko opcodes would be something like this.
  </para>
  
  <refsect1>
    <!--To add examples, create the csd file in the examples directory, then run:-->
    <!--python csd2docbook.py -f newopcodename.csd-->
    <!--to generate the xml highlighted version used below-->
    <title>Example</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the Jacko opcodes. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/jacko.csd"><citetitle>jacko.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the Jacko opcodes.</title>
        <xi:include href="examples-xml/jacko.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>By: &namemichael; 2010</para>
  </refsect1>
  
</chapter>
