<refentry id="diskgrain">
  <indexterm id="Indexdiskgrain"><primary>diskgrain</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Generators:Granular Synthesis</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>diskgrain</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>diskgrain</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Synchronous granular synthesis, using a soundfile as source.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>diskgrain</emphasis> implements synchronous granular synthesis. The source sound for the grains is obtained by reading a soundfile containing the samples of the source waveform. 
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>asig <command>diskgrain</command> Sfname, kamp, kfreq, kpitch, kgrsize, kprate, \
      ifun, iolaps [,imaxgrsize , ioffset]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Sfilename</emphasis> -- source soundfile.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ifun</emphasis> -- grain envelope function table.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>iolaps</emphasis> -- maximum number of overlaps, max(kfreq)*max(kgrsize). Estimating
      a large value should not affect performance, but exceeding this value will probably have disastrous
      consequences.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>imaxgrsize</emphasis> -- max grain size in secs (default 1.0).
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ioffset</emphasis> -- start offset in secs from beginning of file (default: 0).	
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kamp</emphasis> -- amplitude scaling
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis> -- frequency of grain generation, or density, in grains/sec.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis> -- grain pitch scaling (1=normal pitch, &lt; 1 lower, > 1 higher; negative, backwards)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kgrsize</emphasis> -- grain size in secs.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kprate</emphasis> -- readout pointer rate, in
      grains. The value of 1 will advance the reading pointer 1 grain
      ahead in the source table. Larger values will time-compress and
      smaller values will time-expand the source signal.  Negative
      values will cause the pointer to run backwards and zero will
      freeze it.
    </para>
    <para>
      The grain generator has full control of frequency (grains/sec),
      overall amplitude, grain pitch (a sampling increment) and grain
      size (in secs), both as fixed or time-varying (signal)
      parameters.  An extra parameter is the grain pointer speed (or
      rate), which controls which position the generator will start
      reading samples in the file for each successive grain. It is
      measured in fractions of grain size, so a value of 1 (the
      default) will make each successive grain read from where the
      previous grain should finish. A value of 0.5 will make the next
      grain start at the midway position from the previous grain start
      and finish, etc.. A value of 0 will make the generator read
      always from a fixed position (wherever the pointer was last at).
      A negative value will decrement pointer positions. This control
      gives extra flexibility for creating timescale modifications in
      the resynthesis.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Diskgrain</emphasis> will generate any number of
      parallel grain streams (which will depend on grain
      density/frequency), up to the olaps value (default 100). The
      number of streams (overlapped grains) is determined by
      grainsize*grain_freq. More grain overlaps will demand more
      calculations and the synthesis might not run in realtime
      (depending on processor power).
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Diskgrain</emphasis> can simulate FOF-like formant
      synthesis, provided that a suitable shape is used as grain
      envelope and a sinewave as the grain wave. For this use, grain
      sizes of around 0.04 secs can be used. The formant centre
      frequency is determined by the grain pitch.  Since this is a
      sampling increment, in order to use a frequency in Hz, that
      value has to be scaled by tablesize/sr. Grain frequency will
      determine the fundamental.
    </para>
    <para>
      This opcode is a variation on the <link
      linkend="syncgrain"><citetitle>syncgrain</citetitle></link>
      opcode.
    </para>
    <para>
      <note>diskgrain does not do any resanmpling, so if the
      sample rate of the source filename is not the same as csound's sr
      value there will be pitch shifts
      </note>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the diskgrain opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/diskgrain.csd"><citetitle>diskgrain.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the diskgrain opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/diskgrain.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="SiggenGranular"><citetitle>Granular Synthesis</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namevictor;</member>
        <member>May 2007</member>
      </simplelist>
      New in Csound 5.06
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
