
<refentry id="diskin2">
<indexterm id="IndexDiskin2"><primary>diskin2</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal I/O:Signal Input</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>diskin2</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>diskin2</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Reads audio data from a file, and can alter its pitch using one of several
      available interpolation types, as well as convert the sample rate to match
      the orchestra sr setting.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
	Reads audio data from a file, and can alter its pitch using
	one of several available interpolation types, as well as
	convert the sample rate to match the orchestra sr
	setting. <emphasis>diskin2</emphasis> can also read
	multichannel files with any number of channels in the range 1
	to 24 in versions before 5.14, and 40 after. 
	
    </para>


  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>a1[, a2[, ... aN]] <command>diskin2</command> ifilcod[, kpitch[, iskiptim \
      [, iwrap[, iformat[, iwsize[, ibufsize[, iskipinit]]]]]]]</synopsis>

       <synopsis>ar1[] <command>diskin2</command> ifilcod[, kpitch[, iskiptim \
      [, iwrap[, iformat[, iwsize[, ibufsize[, iskipinit]]]]]]]</synopsis>

<para> (in the array output version, the number of output channels does not have an upper limit.)</para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>

	<para>
	<emphasis>ifilcod</emphasis>
	-- integer or character-string denoting the source soundfile
	name. An integer denotes the file soundin.ifilcod; a character-string
   	(in double quotes, spaces permitted) gives the filename itself,
   	optionally a full pathname. If not a full path, the named file is
   	sought first in the current directory, then in those given by the
   	environment variable <link linkend="CommandEnvironment"><citetitle>SSDIR</citetitle></link> (if defined) then by <link linkend="CommandEnvironment"><citetitle>SFDIR</citetitle></link>. See also
    <link linkend="GEN01"><citetitle>GEN01</citetitle></link>.
   	Note: files longer than 2<superscript>31</superscript>-1 sample frames may not be played correctly
   	on 32-bit platforms; this means a maximum length about 3 hours with a
   	sample rate of 192000 Hz.
   	</para>

   	<para>
   	<emphasis>iskiptim</emphasis>
   	(optional, defaults to zero) -- time in seconds of input sound to
   	be skipped, assuming <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis>=1. Can be negative, to add
    -<emphasis>iskiptim</emphasis>/<emphasis>kpitch</emphasis>
   	seconds of delay instead of skipping sound.
    <note>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>If <emphasis>iwrap</emphasis> is not 0 (locations are wrapped),
    <emphasis>iskiptim</emphasis> will not delay the sound if a negative value is used.
    Instead, the negative value will be "wrapped" from the end of the file.
    </para>
    </note>
   	</para>

	<para>
	<emphasis>iwrap</emphasis>
	(optional, defaults to zero) -- if set to any non-zero value, read
   	locations that are negative or are beyond the end of the file are wrapped
   	to the duration of the sound file instead of assuming zero samples.
   	Useful for playing a file in a loop.

   	<note>
   	<title>Note</title>
   	<para>
   	If <emphasis>iwrap</emphasis> is enabled, the file length should not be shorter than
   	the interpolation window size (see below), otherwise there may be clicks
   	in the sound output.
   	</para>
   	</note>

   	</para>

   	<para>
   	<emphasis>iformat</emphasis>
   	(optional, defaults to zero) -- sample format, for raw (headerless)
   	files only. This parameter is ignored if the file has a header.
   	Allowed values are:

	<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>0: 16-bit short integers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>1: 8-bit signed char (high-order 8 bits of a 16-bit integer)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2: 8-bit A-law bytes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>3: 8-bit U-law bytes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>4: 16-bit short integers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>5: 32-bit long integers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>6: 32-bit floats</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>7: 8-bit unsigned int</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>8: 24-bit int</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>9: 64-bit doubles</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

	</para>

	<para>
	<emphasis>iwsize</emphasis>
	(optional, defaults to zero) -- interpolation window size, in samples.
   	Can be one of the following:

   	<itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
			<para>1: round to nearest sample (no interpolation, for <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis>=1)</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>2: linear interpolation</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>4: cubic interpolation</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>>= 8: <emphasis>iwsize</emphasis> point sinc interpolation with anti-aliasing (slow)</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	Zero or negative values select the default, which is cubic interpolation.

  	<note>
  	<title>Note</title>
  	<para>If interpolation is used, <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis> is automatically scaled by the
	ratio of the sample rate of the sound file and the orchestra, so that
    the file will always be played at the original pitch if <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis> is 1.
    However, the sample rate conversion is disabled if <emphasis>iwsize</emphasis> is 1.
    </para>
    </note>

    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>ibufsize</emphasis>
	(optional, defaults to 0) -- buffer size in mono samples (not sample
        frames). This is only the suggested value, the actual setting will be
        rounded so that the number of sample frames is an integer power of two
        and is in the range 128 (or <emphasis>iwsize</emphasis> if greater than 128) to 1048576.
        The default, which is 4096, and is enabled by zero or negative values,
        should be suitable for most uses, but for non-realtime mixing of many
        large sound files, a high buffer setting is recommended to improve the
        efficiency of disk reads. For real time audio output, reading the files
        from a fast RAM file system (on platforms where this option is
        available) with a small buffer size may be preferred.
    </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis>iskipinit</emphasis>
        (optional, defaults to 0) -- skip initialization if set to any
        non-zero value.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>

	<para>
	<emphasis>a1 ... a24</emphasis>
	-- output signals, in the range -0dbfs to 0dbfs. Any samples
    before the beginning (i.e. negative location) and after the end of
    the file are assumed to be zero, unless <emphasis>iwrap</emphasis> is non-zero.
    The number of output arguments must be the same as the number of sound
    file channels - which can be determined with the
    <link linkend="filenchnls"><citetitle>filenchnls</citetitle></link> opcode,
    otherwise an init error will occur.
</para>

	<para>
	<emphasis>ar1[]</emphasis>
         --- output signals, in a-rate array of size N, where N is the number of
             channels in the file. Arrays are automatically allocated to the correct
             size.
	</para>
    <note>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>It is more efficient to read a single file with many channels,
   	than many files with only a single channel, especially with high <emphasis>iwsize</emphasis>
	settings.
	</para>
	</note>

	

	<para>
	<emphasis>kpitch</emphasis>
	-- transpose the pitch of input sound by this factor (e.g. 0.5 means
    one octave lower, 2 is one octave higher, and 1 is the original
    pitch, which is the default value).
    Fractional and negative values are allowed (the latter results in
    playing the file backwards, however, in this case the skip time parameter
    should be set to some positive value, e.g. the length of the file, or
    <emphasis>iwrap</emphasis> should be non-zero, otherwise nothing would be played).
    If interpolation is enabled, and the sample rate of the file differs
    from the orchestra sample rate, the transpose ratio is automatically
    adjusted to make sure that <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis>=1 plays at the original pitch.
    Using a high <emphasis>iwsize</emphasis> setting (40 or more) can significantly improve
    sound quality when transposing up, although at the expense of high
    CPU usage.
    </para>

  </refsect1>


  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the diskin2 opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/diskin2.csd"><citetitle>diskin2.csd</citetitle></ulink>, <ulink url="examples/beats.wav"><citetitle>beats.wav</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the diskin2 opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/diskin2.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="in"><citetitle>in</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="inh"><citetitle>inh</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="ino"><citetitle>ino</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="inq"><citetitle>inq</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="ins"><citetitle>ins</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="soundin"><citetitle>soundin</citetitle></link> and 
      <link linkend="diskin"><citetitle>diskin</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: Istvan Varga</member>
        <member>2005</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>New in version 5.00</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
