<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" id="distort">
<indexterm id="IndexDistort"><primary>distort</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Modifiers:Special Effects</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>distort</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>distort</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Distort an audio signal via waveshaping and optional clipping.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Distort an audio signal via waveshaping and optional clipping.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>ar <command>distort</command> asig, kdist, ifn[, ihp, istor]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> -- table number of a waveshaping
    function with extended guard point.  The function can be of any
    shape, but it should pass through 0 with positive slope at the
    table mid-point.  The table size need not be large, since it is
    read with interpolation. 
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>ihp</emphasis> -- (optional) half-power point (in cps)
    of an internal low-pass filter. The default value is 10. 
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>istor</emphasis> -- (optional) initial disposition of
    internal data space (see reson).  The default value is 0. 
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>asig</emphasis> -- Audio signal to be processed
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> -- Amount of distortion (usually between 0 and
      1)
    </para>
    <para>
      This unit distorts an incoming signal using a waveshaping function
      <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> and a distortion index
      <emphasis>kdist</emphasis>. The input signal is first compressed using a
      running rms, then passed through a waveshaping function which may modify
      its shape and spectrum. Finally it is rescaled to approximately its
      original power.
    </para>
    <para>
       The amount of distortion depends on the nature of the shaping function
       and on the value of <emphasis>kdist</emphasis>, which generally ranges
       from 0 to 1. For low values of <emphasis>kdist</emphasis>, we should like
       the shaping function to pass the signal almost unchanged.  This will be
       the case if, at the mid-point of the table, the shaping function is
       near-linear and is passing through 0 with positive slope.  A line function
       from  -1 to +1 will satisfy this requirement;  so too will a sigmoid
       (sinusoid from 270 to 90 degrees).  As <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> is
       increased, the compressed signal is expanded to encounter more and more
       of the shaping function, and if this becomes non-linear the signal is
       increasingly <emphasis>bent</emphasis> on read-through to cause
       distortion.
     </para>
    <para>
    When <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> becomes large enough, the read-through process will
    eventually hit the outer limits of the table.  The table is not
    read with wrap-around, but will <quote>stick</quote> at the end-points as the
    incoming signal exceeds them;  this introduces clipping, an
    additional form of signal distortion.  The point at which clipping
    begins will depend on the complexity (rms-to-peak value) of the
    input signal.  For a pure sinusoid, clipping will begin only as
    <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> exceeds 0.7;  for a more complex input, clipping might begin
    at a <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> of 0.5 or much less.  <emphasis>kdist</emphasis> can exceed
    the clip point by any amount, and may be greater than 1. 
    </para>
    <para>
    The shaping function can be made arbitrarily complex for extra effect.
    It should generally be continuous, though this is not a
    requirement.  It should also be well-behaved near the mid-point,
    and roughly balanced positive-negative overall, else some
    excessive DC offset may result.  The user might experiment with
    more aggressive functions to suit the purpose.  A generally
    positive slope allows the distorted signal to be mixed with the
    source without phase cancellation. 
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>distort</emphasis> is useful as an effects process, and is usually combined with
    reverb and chorusing on effects busses.  However, it can
    alternatively be used to good effect within a single instrument. 
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the distort opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/distort.csd"><citetitle>distort.csd</citetitle></ulink>.

      <example>
        <title>Example of the distort opcode.</title>      

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples-xml/distort.csd.xml"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Written by Barry L. Vercoe for Extended Csound and released in Csound5.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
