
<refentry id="FLsetSnapGroup">
<indexterm id="IndexFLsetSnapGroup"><primary>FLsetSnapGroup</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>FLTK:Other</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>FLsetSnapGroup</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>FLsetSnapGroup</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Determines the snapshot group for FL valuators.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
    Plugin opcode in widgets. This opcode is part of the plugin repository and has to be installed separately. These FLTK widgets do not work on the Mac. 
    The plugin repository can be found here: <ulink url="https://github.com/csound/plugins"><citetitle>https://github.com/csound/plugins</citetitle></ulink></para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> determines the snapshot group of valuators declared after it.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis><command>FLsetSnapGroup</command> igroup</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>igroup</emphasis> -- (optional) an integer number referring to a snapshot-related group of widget. It allows to get/set, or to load/save the state of a subset of valuators.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        The <emphasis>igroup</emphasis> parameter has not been yet fully implemented in the current version of csound. Please do not rely on it yet.
      </para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      For purposes of snapshot saving, widgets can be grouped, so that snapshots affect only a defined group of widgets. The opcode <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> is used to specify the group for all widgets declared after it, until the next <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> statement.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> determines the snapshot group of a declared valuator. To make a valuator belong to a stated group, you have to place <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> just before the declaration of the widget itself. The group stated by <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> lasts for all valuators declared after it, until a new <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> statement with a different group is encountered. If no <emphasis>FLsetSnapGroup</emphasis> statement are present in an orchestra, the default group for all widgets will be group zero.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="FLgetsnap"><citetitle>FLgetsnap</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="FLsetsnap"><citetitle>FLsetsnap</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="FLloadsnap"><citetitle>FLloadsnap</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="FLsavesnap"><citetitle>FLsavesnap</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Author: &namegabriel;</para>
    <para>New in version 4.22</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
