
<refentry id="freeverb">
<indexterm id="IndexFreeverb"><primary>freeverb</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Modifiers:Reverberation</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>freeverb</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>



  <refnamediv>
    <refname>freeverb</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Opcode version of Jezar's Freeverb
          </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
		freeverb is a stereo reverb unit based on Jezar's public domain
		C++ sources, composed of eight parallel comb filters on both
		channels, followed by four allpass units in series. The filters
		on the right channel are slightly detuned compared to the left
		channel in order to create a stereo effect.
    </para>


  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>aoutL, aoutR <command>freeverb</command> ainL, ainR, kRoomSize, kHFDamp[, iSRate[, iSkip]] </synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>

    <para>
      <emphasis>iSRate</emphasis>
      (optional, defaults to 44100): adjusts the reverb parameters for
    use with the specified sample rate (this will affect the length of
    the delay lines in samples, and, as of the latest CVS version, the
    high frequency attenuation). Only integer multiples of 44100 will
    reproduce the original character of the reverb exactly, so it may
    be useful to set this to 44100 or 88200 for an orchestra sample
    rate of 48000 or 96000 Hz, respectively. While iSRate is normally
    expected to be close to the orchestra sample rate, different
    settings may be useful for special effects.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>iSkip</emphasis>
      (optional, defaults to zero): if non-zero, initialization of the
    opcode will be skipped, whenever possible.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
     <para>
      <emphasis>ainL, ainR</emphasis>
      -- input signals; usually both are the same, but different
    inputs can be used for special effect

    <note>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>It is recommended to process the input signal(s) with the
    denorm opcode in order to avoid denormalized numbers which could
    significantly increase CPU usage in some cases
    </para>
    </note>

    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>aoutL, aoutR</emphasis>
      -- output signals for left and right channel
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kRoomSize</emphasis>
      (range: 0 to 1) -- controls the length of the reverb, a higher
      value means longer reverb. Settings above 1 may make the opcode
      unstable.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kHFDamp</emphasis>
      (range: 0 to 1): high frequency attenuation; a value of zero
    means all frequencies decay at the same rate, while higher settings
    will result in a faster decay of the high frequency range.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the <emphasis>freeverb</emphasis> opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/freeverb.csd"><citetitle>freeverb.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>An example of the freeverb opcode.</title>

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
        <xi:include href="examples-xml/freeverb.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

      <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para><link linkend="SigmodReverbtn"><citetitle>Reverberation</citetitle></link></para>
    </refsect1>
	
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: Istvan Varga</member>
        <member>2005</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
