
<refentry id="liveconv">
<indexterm id="IndexLiveconv"><primary>liveconv</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Modifiers:Convolution and Morphing</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>liveconv</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>liveconv</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Partitioned convolution with dynamically reloadable impulse response
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>Plugin opcode in liveconv.</para>
    <para>
	    Computationally efficient, partitioned convolution, using a function table as impulse response (IR) source,
      similar to the <link linkend="ftconv"><citetitle>ftconv</citetitle></link> opcode. 
      The <emphasis>liveconv</emphasis> opcode allows dynamic reload of IR data at any time
      while the convolution is running, controlled by the <emphasis>kupdate</emphasis> parameter.
      Due to the manner in which the IR is updated, the operation can be done without audio artifacts in the convolution output.
      </para>
  
    <para>
      The IR table is read partition by partition after signalling an update. 
      The first <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> samples must be available when the update flag is set. 
      The rest of the table can be continuously filled in consecutive passes. There may be a new update 
      for every partition, allowing as many as <emphasis>ftlen/iplen</emphasis> simultaneous updates
      (ftlen is the length of the IR table).
      </para>

    <para>
      The low-latency, dynamic behavior of <emphasis>liveconv</emphasis> makes it ideal for
      convolution with live sampled impulse responses, and/or real-time impulse response transformations and modifications.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>ares <command>liveconv</command> ain, ift, iplen, kupdate, kclear</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>

	  <para>
  	  <emphasis>ift</emphasis>
	    -- table number for storing the impulse response (IR) for convolution. The table may be filled with new
      data at any time while the convolution is running.
     </para>

	  <para>
	    <emphasis>iplen</emphasis>
	    -- length of impulse response partition in samples; must be an
      integer power of two. Lower settings allow for shorter output delay, but
      will increase CPU usage.
      </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>

     <para>
      <emphasis>ain</emphasis>
      -- input signal.
      </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>ares</emphasis>
      -- output signal.
      </para>

 	  <para>
  	  <emphasis>kupdate</emphasis>
	    -- flag indicating whether the IR table should be updated.
      If kupdate=1 the IR table ift is loaded partition by partition, starting with the next partition.
      If kupdate=-1 the IR table ift is unloaded (cleared to zero) partition by partition, starting with the next partition.
      Other values have no effect.
      </para>

   	<para>
  	  <emphasis>kclear</emphasis>
	    -- flag for clearing all internal buffers.
      If kclear has any value != zero, the internal buffers are cleared immediately. This operation is not free of artifacts.
      </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Example</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the liveconv opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/liveconv.csd"><citetitle>liveconv.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the liveconv opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
       <xi:include href="examples-xml/liveconv.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

      <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para><link linkend="SigProcConmorph"><citetitle>Convolution and Morphing</citetitle></link></para>
    </refsect1>
	
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: Sigurd Saue, Oeyvind Brandtsegg</member>
        <member>2017</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
