
<refentry id="loopseg">
<indexterm id="IndexLoopseg"><primary>loopseg</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Generators:Linear and Exponential Generators</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>loopseg</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>loopseg</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Generate control signal consisting of linear segments delimited by two or more specified points.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Generate control signal consisting of linear segments delimited by two or more specified points. The entire envelope is looped at <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis> rate. Each parameter can be varied at k-rate.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>ksig <command>loopseg</command> kfreq, ktrig, iphase, ktime0, kvalue0 [, ktime1] [, kvalue1] \
      [, ktime2] [, kvalue2] [...]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ksig</emphasis> -- Output signal.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis> -- Repeat rate in Hz or fraction of Hz.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>ktrig</emphasis> -- If non-zero, retriggers the envelope from start (see <link linkend="trigger"><citetitle>trigger opcode</citetitle></link>), before the envelope cycle is completed.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>iphase</emphasis> -- A value between 0 and 1 to say
      where to start the loop.  Zero, the commonest value, indicates
      the beginning.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>ktime0...ktimeN</emphasis> -- Times of points; expressed in fraction of a cycle.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kvalue0...kvalueN</emphasis> -- Values of points
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>loopseg</emphasis> opcode is similar to <link linkend="linseg"><citetitle>linseg</citetitle></link>, but the entire envelope is looped at <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis> rate. Notice that times are not expressed in seconds but in fraction of a cycle. Actually each duration represent is proportional to the other, and the entire cycle duration is proportional to the sum of all duration values.  
    </para>

    <para>
      The sum of all duration is then rescaled according to <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis> argument. For example, considering an envelope made up of 3 segments, each segment having 100 as duration value, their sum will be 300. This value represents the total duration of the envelope, and is actually divided into 3 equal parts, a part for each segment.
    </para>

    <para>
      Actually, the real envelope duration in seconds is determined by <emphasis>kfreq</emphasis>. Again, if the envelope is made up of 3 segments, but this time the first and last segments have a duration of 50, whereas the central segment has a duration of 100 again, their sum will be 200. This time 200 represent the total duration of the 3 segments, so the central segment will be twice as long as the other segments.
    </para>

    <para>
      All parameters can be varied at k-rate.  Negative frequency values are allowed, reading the envelope backward.  <emphasis>ktime0</emphasis> should always be set to 0, except if the user wants some special effect.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the loopseg opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/loopseg.csd"><citetitle>loopseg.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the loopseg opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/loopseg.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="lpshold"><citetitle>lpshold</citetitle></link>
      <link linkend="loopxseg"><citetitle>loopxseg</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Author: &namegabriel;</para>
    <para>New in Version 4.13</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
