
<refentry id="lpcfilter">
<indexterm id="IndexLpcanal"><primary>lpcanal</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Spectral Processing:LPC</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>lpcanal</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>lpcanal</refname>
    <refpurpose>
    Streaming linear prediction analysis.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
     This opcode implements streaming linear prediction analysis. Two versions
     exist, one taking input from an audio signal, and the other from
     a function table.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>kCoef[],krms,kerr,kcps <command>lpcanal</command> asrc, kflg,
    kprd, isiz, iord[,iwin] </synopsis>
    <synopsis>kCoef[],krms,kerr,kcps <command>lpcanal</command> koff, kflg,
    ifn, isiz, iord[,iwin] </synopsis>
    <synopsis>iCoef[],irms,ierr,icps <command>lpcanal</command> ioff, iflg,
    ifn, isiz, iord[,iwin] </synopsis>
    
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>isiz</emphasis> -- size of lpc input frame in samples.
    </para>

        <para>
      <emphasis>iord</emphasis> -- linear predictor order.
        </para>

       <para>
      <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> -- streaming LPC analysis source function table
    </para>

        <para>
      <emphasis>iwin</emphasis> -- window function table number (optional)
        </para>
    
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kCoef[]</emphasis> -- all-pole filter coefficients
      (iord-size array)
    </para>

        <para>
      <emphasis>krms</emphasis> - RMS estimate of source signal.
        </para>

         <para>
      <emphasis>kerr</emphasis> - linear prediction error (or residual).
         </para>

         <para>
      <emphasis>kcps</emphasis> - fundamental frequency estimate, from
      the autocorrelation function.
    </para>             

        <para>
      <emphasis>asrc</emphasis> -- streaming LPC analysis source signal
        </para>

     <para>
      <emphasis>kflg</emphasis> -- compute flag, non-zero values
      switch on linear prediction analysis replacing filter coefficients, zero switch it off,
      keeping current filter coefficients.
    </para>

     <para>
      <emphasis>kprd</emphasis> -- analysis period in samples,
      determining how often new coefficients are computed.
     </para>

     <para>
       <emphasis>koff</emphasis> -- function table position offset, in
       samples, determining the start position of analysis frame.
    </para>       
  </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
   <para>
        This opcode is part of a suite of streaming linear prediction
        opcodes. It analyses an input signal, either as an audio input
        or stored in a function table and produces a set of
        coefficients for an all-pole filter that models the signal's
        spectral envelope. These opcodes are placed in a k-rate array,
        and output along with other analysis measurements.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The fundamental analysis parameters are input frame size and
      filter order. Longer input frames will produce a more accurate
      result in terms of frequency resolution, but will also involve
      more computation. This is due to the computation of the
      autocorrelation function, which is then used in the coefficient
      computation. This part is more efficient and depends only
      on the linear prediction order, which is also the number of
      coefficients computed. Typical lp orders may range from
      about 30 to 100 coefficients, but larger values can also
      be used.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If the LPC source signal is derived from an audio input, then
      the computation of coefficients is dependent on two parameters,
      kflg and kprd. The first is an on/off switch that determines
      whether coefficients are replaced by newly-computed ones
      or the coefficients are kept fixed to their last value. The
      other determines the frequency of analyses, by setting a
      time interval (in samples) between new coefficient computation.
      This ranges from coefficients being replaced every sample,
      to never replaced (if the period is larger than the synthesis duration).
      Overlapped analyses will take place if the value of kprd is less
      than the input size. Decreasng the spacing of analyses will
      also increase computation demands.
      </para>
      <para>
        If the LPC source signal is derived from a function table,
        then kflg determines wheter an analysis should be performed
        or not (1 or 0). The value of koff is then used as an offset
        (in samples) into the function table determining the position
        of the analysis frame. For example, if kflg is permanently set
        to 1 and koff is set to ksmps, then at every kcycle an
        analysis frame will be taken from successive positions in the
        function table. Changing koff to fewer samples will produce
        a timestretched result and increasing it will time compress.
      </para>
      <para>
       Once the signal is extracted from either an audio input or
       function table then it can be optionally windowed if a function
       table is provided. While this is optional, it is a recommended
       procedure (GEN20 can provide the most common windows).
       The signal is then analysed and coefficients produced.
      </para>
      
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the lpcanal opcode using an audio input
      signal as lpc source. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/lpcanal.csd"><citetitle>lpcanal.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the lpcanal opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/lpcanal.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
       <para>
      Here is another example of the lpcanal opcode, now using a
      function table as lpc source. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/lpcanal-2.csd"><citetitle>lpcanal-2.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Another example of the lpcanal opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/lpcanal-2.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="lpcfilter"><citetitle>lpcfilter</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="allpole"><citetitle>allpole</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
