
<refentry id="MixerSetLevel_i">
  <indexterm id="IndexMixerSetLevel_i"><primary>MixerSetLevel_i</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Mixer Opcodes</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>MixerSetLevel_i</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
  
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>MixerSetLevel_i</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Sets the level of a send to a buss.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis><command>MixerSetLevel_i</command> isend, ibuss, igain</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title> 
    <para>Sets the level at which signals from the send are added to the buss. This opcode, because all parameters are irate, may 
      be used in the orchestra header. The actual sending of the signal to the buss 
      is performed by the <link linkend="MixerSend"><citetitle>MixerSend</citetitle></link> opcode. 
    </para>  
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    
    <para><emphasis>isend</emphasis> -- The number of the send, for example the number of the instrument sending the signal (but any integer can be used).</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>ibuss</emphasis> -- The number of the buss, for example the number of the instrument receiving the signal (but any integer can be used).</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>igain</emphasis> -- The level (any real number) at which the signal from the send will be mixed onto the buss. The default is 0.</para>
    
    <para>Setting the gain for a buss also creates the buss.</para>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    
    <para>
      Use of the mixer requires that instruments setting gains have smaller numbers than instruments sending signals, 
      and that instruments sending signals have smaller numbers than instruments receiving those signals. 
      However, an instrument may have any number of sends or receives. After the final signal is received, 
      <link linkend="MixerClear"><citetitle>MixerClear</citetitle></link> must be invoked to reset the busses before the next kperiod.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    
    <para>In the orchestra header, set the gain for the send from buss 3 to buss 4:</para>
    <programlisting>
      <emphasis role="opc">MixerSetLevel_i</emphasis>		3, 4, 0.76</programlisting>
    
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Michael Gogins (gogins at pipeline dot com).</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
