
<refentry id="outkc14">
<indexterm id="IndexOutkc14"><primary>outkc14</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Real-time MIDI:Output</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>outkc14</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>


 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>outkc14</refname>

    <refpurpose>
      Sends 14-bit MIDI controller output at k-rate.
          </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Sends 14-bit MIDI controller output at k-rate.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis><command>outkc14</command> kchn, kmsb, klsb, kvalue, kmin, kmax</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kchn</emphasis> -- MIDI channel number (1-16)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kmsb</emphasis> -- most significant byte controller number when using 14-bit parameters (0-127)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>klsb</emphasis> -- least significant byte controller number when using 14-bit parameters (0-127)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kvalue</emphasis> -- floating point value
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kmin</emphasis> -- minimum floating point value (converted in MIDI integer value 0)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kmax</emphasis> -- maximum floating point value (converted in MIDI integer value 16383 (14-bit))
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>outkc14</emphasis> (k-rate MIDI 14-bit controller output) sends a pair of controller messages. It works only with MIDI instruments which recognize them. These opcodes can drive 14-bit parameters on MIDI instruments that recognize them. The first control message contains the most significant byte of <emphasis>kvalue</emphasis> argument while the second message contains the less significant byte. <emphasis>kmsb</emphasis> and <emphasis>klsb</emphasis> are the number of the most and less significant controller.
    </para>

    <para>
      It can drive a different value of a parameter for each note currently active. 
    </para>

    <para>
      It can scale the k-value floating-point argument according to the <emphasis>kmin</emphasis> and <emphasis>kmax</emphasis> values. For example: set <emphasis>kmin</emphasis> = 1.0 and <emphasis>kmax</emphasis> = 2.0.
When the <emphasis>kvalue</emphasis> argument receives a 2.0 value, the opcode will send a 127 value to the MIDI OUT device. When the <emphasis>kvalue</emphasis> argument receives a 1.0 value, it will send a 0 value. k-rate opcodes send a message each time the MIDI converted value of argument <emphasis>kvalue</emphasis> changes.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  
      <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para><link linkend="MidiOutput"><citetitle>MIDI Message Output</citetitle></link></para>
    </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namegabriel;</member>
        <member>Italy</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>

    <para>New in Csound version 3.47</para>
    <para>Thanks goes to &namerasmus; for pointing out the correct MIDI channel and controller number ranges.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
