
<refentry id="pvs2tab">
<indexterm id="IndexPvs2tab"><primary>pvs2tab</primary></indexterm>

  <refentryinfo><title>Spectral Processing:Streaming</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pvs2tab</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>pvs2tab</refname>
    <refpurpose>
     Copies spectral data to k-rate arrays (or t-variables). Also known as pvs2array.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
       Copies a pvs frame to a t-variable. Currently only AMP+FREQ and AMP+PHASE formats allowed. Since t-vars are an earlier version of k-rate arrays, the opcode also works with these. The opcode pvs2array is an alias of this one.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>kframe <command>pvs2tab</command> tvar|kvar[], fsig</synopsis>
    <synopsis>kframe <command>pvs2tab</command> kmags[], kfreqs[], fsig</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kframe</emphasis> -- current copied frame number. It can be used to detect when a new frame has been copied.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>tvar|kvar[]</emphasis> -- t-variable or k-rate array containing the output. It is produced at every k-period, but may not contain a new frame, pvs frames are produced at their own frame rate that is independent of kr. Generally, this vector needs to be big enough to contain the frame samples, i.e. N+2 (N is the dft size). If smaller, only a portion of the frame will be copied; if bigger, unused points will exist at higher indexes. 
    </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis>kmags[], kfreqs[]</emphasis> k-rate arrays containing magnitude and frequency values. These arrays need to be generally be of size N/2 + 1, where N is dft frame size. If smaller, only a portion of the pvs frame will be copied; if bigger, unused points will exist at higher indexes.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>fsig</emphasis> -- input fsig to be copied.
    </para>
  
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      <example>
        <title>Example</title>
        <programlisting>
karr[] init 1026
a1 inch 1
fsig1   pvsanal a1, 1024,256,1024, 1
kframe  <emphasis role="opc">pvs2tab</emphasis>karr, fsig1</programlisting>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namevictor;</member>
        <member>October 2011 </member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>

    <para>New plugin in version 5</para>
    <para>October 2011.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
