
<refentry id="pvstencil">
<indexterm id="IndexPvstencil"><primary>pvstencil</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Spectral Processing:Streaming</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pvstencil</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>pvstencil</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Transforms a pvoc stream according to a masking function table.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Transforms a pvoc stream according to a masking function table;
      if the pvoc stream amplitude falls below the value of the function
      for a specific pvoc channel, it applies a gain to that channel.
    </para>
    <para>
      The pvoc stream amplitudes are compared to a masking table, if
      the fall below the table values, they are scaled by <emphasis>kgain</emphasis>. Prior
      to the operation, table values are scaled by <emphasis>klevel</emphasis>, which can be
      used as masking depth control.
    </para>
    <para>
    Tables have to be at least fftsize/2 in size; for most GENS it is
    important to use an extended-guard point (size power-of-two plus
    one), however this is not necessary with GEN43.
    </para>
    <para>
    One of the typical uses of <emphasis>pvstencil</emphasis> would be in noise
    reduction. A noise print can be analysed with <emphasis>pvanal</emphasis> into a PVOC-EX
    file and loaded in a table with <emphasis>GEN43</emphasis>. This then can be used as
    the masking table for <emphasis>pvstencil</emphasis> and the amount of reduction would
    be controlled by <emphasis>kgain</emphasis>. Skipping post-normalisation will keep the
    original noise print average amplitudes. This would provide a good
    starting point for a successful noise reduction (so that <emphasis>klevel</emphasis>
    can be generally set to close to 1).
    </para>
    <para>
    Other possible transformation effects are possible, such as
    filtering and `inverse-masking'.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>fsig <command>pvstencil</command> fsigin, kgain, klevel, iftable</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>fsig</emphasis> -- output pv stream
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>fsigin</emphasis> -- input pv stream.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kgain</emphasis> -- `stencil' gain.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>klevel</emphasis> -- masking function level (scales
      the ftable prior to `stenciling') .
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>iftable</emphasis> -- masking function table.
    </para>

    <warning>
      <para>
        It is unsafe to use the same f-variable for both input and output of pvs opcodes. Using the same one might lead to undefined behavior on some opcodes. Use a different one on the left and right sides of the opcode.
      </para>
    </warning>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the pvstencil opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/pvstencil.csd"><citetitle>pvstencil.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the pvstencil opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/pvstencil.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namevictor;</member>
        <member>November 2004 </member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>

    <para>New plugin in version 5</para>
    <para>November 2004.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
