
<refentry id="resyn">
<indexterm id="Indexresyn"><primary>resyn</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Spectral Processing:Streaming</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>resyn</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>



  <refnamediv>
    <refname>resyn</refname>
    <refpurpose>
    Streaming partial track additive synthesis with cubic phase interpolation with
pitch control and support for timescale-modified input
          </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
  The resyn opcode takes an input containg a TRACKS pv streaming signal (as generated,
  for instance by partials). It resynthesises the signal using linear amplitude and cubic phase
  interpolation to drive a bank of interpolating oscillators with amplitude and pitch scaling controls. Resyn is
  a modified version of sinsyn, allowing for the resynthesis of data with pitch and timescale changes.
	      </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>asig <command>resyn</command> fin, kscal, kpitch, kmaxtracks, ifn</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
	    <para>
      <emphasis>asig</emphasis> -- output audio rate signal
    </para>
	
    <para>
      <emphasis>fin</emphasis> -- input pv stream in TRACKS format
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kscal</emphasis> -- amplitude scaling
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kpitch</emphasis> -- pitch scaling
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kmaxtracks</emphasis> -- max number of tracks in resynthesis. Limiting this will cause
	  a non-linear filtering effect, by discarding newer and higher-frequency tracks (tracks are ordered
	  by start time and ascending frequency, respectively)
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> -- function table containing one cycle of a sinusoid (sine or cosine) </para>   
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the resyn opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/resyn.csd"><citetitle>resyn.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the resyn opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/resyn.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
    <para>The example above shows partial tracking of an ifd-analysis signal and cubic-phase additive resynthesis with pitch shifting. </para>  
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namevictor;</member>
        <member>June 2005 </member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>

    <para>New plugin in version 5</para>
    <para>November 2004.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
