<refentry id="STKShakers">
  <indexterm id="IndexStkshakers"><primary>STKShakers</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Generators:STK Opcodes</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>STKShakers</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>STKShakers</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      STKShakers is an instrument that simulates environmental sounds or collisions of multiple independent sound producing objects. </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
    STKShakers are a set of PhISEM and PhOLIES instruments: 
      PhISEM (Physically Informed Stochastic Event Modeling) is an algorithmic approach for simulating collisions of multiple independent sound producing objects. 
      It can simulate a Maraca, Sekere, Cabasa, Bamboo Wind Chimes, Water Drops, Tambourine, Sleighbells, and a Guiro. On <ulink url="http://soundlab.cs.princeton.edu/research/controllers/shakers/"></ulink>
PhOLIES (Physically-Oriented Library of Imitated Environmental Sounds) there is a similar approach for the synthesis of environmental sounds. 
It simulates of breaking sticks, crunchy snow (or not), a wrench, sandpaper, and more..</para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>asignal <command>STKShakers</command> ifrequency, iamplitude, [kenerg, kv1[, kdecay, kv2[, kshake, kv3[, knum, kv4[, kres, kv5[, kinstr, kv6]]]]]]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ifrequency</emphasis> -- Frequency of note played, in Hertz.
    </para>
   
    <para>
      <emphasis>iamplitude</emphasis> -- Amplitude of note played (range 0-1).
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
<para><emphasis>kenerg</emphasis> -- controller 2, shake energy. Value range of kv1 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kdecay</emphasis> -- controller 4, system decay. Value range of kv2 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kshake</emphasis> -- controller 128, shake energy. Value range of kv3 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>knum</emphasis> -- controller 11, number of objects. Value range of kv4 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kres</emphasis> -- controller 1, resonance frequency. Value range of kv5 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kinstr</emphasis> -- controller 1071, instrument selection (Maraca = 0, Cabasa = 1, Sekere = 2, Guiro = 3, Water Drops = 4, Bamboo Chimes = 5, Tambourine = 6, Sleigh Bells = 7, Sticks = 8, Crunch = 9, Wrench = 10, Sand Paper = 11, Coke Can = 12, Next Mug = 13, Penny + Mug = 14, Nickle + Mug = 15, Dime + Mug = 16, Quarter + Mug = 17, Franc + Mug = 18, Peso + Mug = 19, Big Rocks = 20, Little Rocks = 21, Tuned Bamboo Chimes = 22). Value range of kv6 is 0-22.</para>
  </refsect1>
 
    <refsect1>
    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>
         The code for this opcode is taken directly from the Shakers class in the Synthesis Toolkit in C++ by Perry R. Cook and Gary P. Scavone. More on the STK classes can be found here:  
<ulink url="https://ccrma.stanford.edu/software/stk/classes.html"><citetitle>https://ccrma.stanford.edu/software/stk/classes.html</citetitle></ulink>
</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>kc1, kv1, kc2, kv2, kc3, kv3, kc4, kv4, kc5, kv5, kc6, kv6, kc7, kv7, kc8, kv8</emphasis> -- Up to 8 optional k-rate controller pairs for the STK opcodes.
      Each controller pair consists of a controller number (kc) followed by a controller value (kv). Both the controller numbers and the controller values are krate variables. However, during a performance, normally the controller numbers stay fixed while the corresponding controller values may change at any time.
The order of the controller pair is arbitrary, as long as they are after <emphasis>iamplitude</emphasis>. Also, it is not needed that all controller pairs are used.
</para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the STKShakers opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/STKShakers.csd"><citetitle>STKShakerscsd</citetitle></ulink>.
     
      <example>
        <title>Example of the STKShakers opcode.</title>
        <xi:include href="examples-xml/STKShakers.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namemichael; (after Georg Essl)</member>
        <member>Irreducible Productions</member>
        <member>New York, NY</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>New in Csound version 5.11</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>

