<refentry id="STKTubeBell">
  <indexterm id="IndexStktubebell"><primary>STKTubeBell</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Generators:STK Opcodes</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>STKTubeBell</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>STKTubeBell</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      STKTubeBell is a  tubular bell (orchestral chime) FM synthesis instrument. 
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>Plugin opcode in stkopd. This opcode is part of the plugin repository and has to be installed separately. 
    The plugin repository can be found here: <ulink url="https://github.com/csound/plugins"><citetitle>https://github.com/csound/plugins</citetitle></ulink></para>
    <para>
      STKTubeBell is a tubular bell (orchestral chime) FM synthesis instrument. 
      It uses two simple FM Pairs summed together, also referred to as algorithm 5 of the TX81Z.</para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>asignal <command>STKTubeBell</command> ifrequency, iamplitude, [kmod, kv1[, kcross, kv2[, klfo, kv3[, klfodepth, kv4[, kadsr, kv5]]]]]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
      <para>
      <emphasis>ifrequency</emphasis> -- Frequency of note played, in Hertz.
    </para>
   
    <para>
      <emphasis>iamplitude</emphasis> -- Amplitude of note played (range 0-1).
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
<para><emphasis>kmod</emphasis> -- controller 2, modulator index 1. Value range of kv1 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kcross</emphasis> -- controller 4, crossfade of outputs. Value range of kv2 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>klfo</emphasis> -- controller 11, speed of low-frequency oscillator. Value range of kv3 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>klfodepth</emphasis> -- controller 1, depth of low-frequency oscillator. Value range of kv4 is 0-127.</para>
<para><emphasis>kadsr</emphasis> -- controller 128, ADSR 2 and 4 target. Value range of kv5 is 0-127.</para>
  </refsect1>
 
    <refsect1>
    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>
         The code for this opcode is taken directly from the TubeBell class in the Synthesis Toolkit in C++ by Perry R. Cook and Gary P. Scavone. More on the STK classes can be found here:  
<ulink url="https://ccrma.stanford.edu/software/stk/classes.html"><citetitle>https://ccrma.stanford.edu/software/stk/classes.html</citetitle></ulink>
</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>kc1, kv1, kc2, kv2, kc3, kv3, kc4, kv4, kc5, kv5, kc6, kv6, kc7, kv7, kc8, kv8</emphasis> -- Up to 8 optional k-rate controller pairs for the STK opcodes.
      Each controller pair consists of a controller number (kc) followed by a controller value (kv). Both the controller numbers and the controller values are krate variables. However, during a performance, normally the controller numbers stay fixed while the corresponding controller values may change at any time.
The order of the controller pair is arbitrary, as long as they are after <emphasis>iamplitude</emphasis>. Also, it is not needed that all controller pairs are used.
</para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the STKTubeBell opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/STKTubeBell.csd"><citetitle>STKTubeBell.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
     
      <example>
        <title>Example of the STKTubeBell opcode.</title>
        <xi:include href="examples-xml/STKTubeBell.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
      
     <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para><link linkend="STKTop"><citetitle>STK Opcodes</citetitle></link></para>
  </refsect1>
   
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namemichael; (after &nameperry;)</member>
        <member>Irreducible Productions</member>
        <member>New York, NY</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>New in Csound version 5.11</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>

