
<refentry id="svfilter">
<indexterm id="IndexSvfilter"><primary>svfilter</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Modifiers:Standard Filters:Resonant</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>svfilter</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>


 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>svfilter</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      A resonant second order filter, with simultaneous lowpass, highpass and bandpass outputs.
          </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Implementation of a resonant second order filter, with simultaneous lowpass, highpass and bandpass outputs.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>alow, ahigh, aband <command>svfilter</command>  asig, kcf, kq [, iscl] [, iskip]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>iscl</emphasis> -- coded scaling factor, similar to
      that in <link
      linkend="reson"><citetitle>reson</citetitle></link>. A non-zero
      value signifies a peak response factor of 1, i.e. all
      frequencies other than <emphasis>kcf</emphasis> are attenuated
      in accordance with the (normalized) response curve. A zero value
      signifies no scaling of the signal, leaving that to some later
      adjustment (see <link
      linkend="balance"><citetitle>balance</citetitle></link>). The
      default value is 0.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>iskip</emphasis> (optional, default=0) -- initial
      disposition of internal data space. Since filtering incorporates
      a feedback loop of previous output, the initial status of the
      storage space used is significant. A zero value will clear the
      space; a non-zero value will allow previous information to
      remain. The default value is 0.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 

  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>svfilter</emphasis> is a second order state-variable filter, with k-rate controls for cutoff frequency and Q.  As Q is increased, a resonant peak forms around the cutoff frequency. <emphasis>svfilter</emphasis> has simultaneous lowpass, highpass, and bandpass filter outputs; by mixing the outputs together, a variety of frequency responses can be generated. The state-variable filter, or &quot;multimode&quot; filter was a common feature in early analog synthesizers, due to the wide variety of sounds available from the interaction between cutoff, resonance, and output mix ratios. <emphasis>svfilter</emphasis> is well suited to the emulation of &quot;analog&quot; sounds, as well as other applications where resonant filters are called for.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kcf</emphasis> -- Cutoff or resonant frequency of the filter, measured in Hz.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kq</emphasis> -- Q of the filter, which is defined (for bandpass filters) as bandwidth/cutoff. <emphasis>kq</emphasis> should be in a range between 1 and 500. As <emphasis>kq</emphasis> is increased, the resonance of the filter increases, which corresponds to an increase in the magnitude and &quot;sharpness&quot; of the resonant peak. When using <emphasis>svfilter</emphasis> without any scaling of the signal (where <emphasis>iscl</emphasis> is either absent or 0), the volume of the resonant peak increases as Q increases. For high values of Q, it is recommended that <emphasis>iscl</emphasis> be set to a non-zero value, or that an external scaling function such as <link linkend="balance"><citetitle>balance</citetitle></link> is used.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>svfilter</emphasis> is based upon an algorithm in Hal Chamberlin's <emphasis>Musical Applications of Microprocessor</emphasis>s (Hayden Books, 1985).
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the svfilter opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/svfilter.csd"><citetitle>svfilter.csd</citetitle></ulink>.

      <example>
        <title>Example of the svfilter opcode.</title>

        

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/svfilter.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  
     <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para><link linkend="SigmodStandard"><citetitle>Resonant Low-pass filters</citetitle></link></para>
    </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namesean;</member>
        <member>Seattle, Washington</member>
        <member>1999</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>

    <para>New in Csound version 3.55</para>
    <para>iskip new in version 6.06</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
