<refentry id="svn">
<indexterm id="IndexSvn"><primary>svn</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal Modifiers:Standard Filters:Resonant</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>svn</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>svn</refname>
    <refpurpose>
     Non-linear state variable filter
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsect1>
<title>Description</title>
    <para>
     This opcode implements a non-linear state variable filter with
     overdrive control and optional user-defined non-linear transfer function.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>ahp,alp,abp,abr <command>svn</command> asig, xcf, xQ,
    kdrive[, ifn,inm,imx, istor]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
      <para>
      <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> -- if non-zero, a function table number
      containing the transfer function for the filter non-linearity. This
      should be mid-point centered and defined in the interval -imx to
      imx. If zero, the filter employs an internal non-linear map
      based on a hyperbolic tangent. Defaults to 0.  
      </para>
            <para>
      <emphasis>inm</emphasis> -- if non-zero, a function table number
      containing a normalising transfer function, generated from ifn
      (using GEN 4). Defaults to 0.    
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>imx</emphasis> -- The absolute max of the function
        table domain, which is defined as  -imx to imx. Defaults to 1.
      </para>
      <para>
      <emphasis>istor</emphasis> --initial disposition of internal
      data space. Since filtering incorporates a feedback loop of
      previous output, the initial status of the storage space used is
      significant.  A zero value will clear the space; a non-zero
      value will allow previous information to remain. The default
      value is 0.
    </para>
      
  </refsect1>
  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
      <para>
      <emphasis>ahp,alp,abp,abr</emphasis> -- highpass, lowpass,
      bandpass and bandreject ouputs.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>asig</emphasis> -- input
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>xcf</emphasis> -- filter
      cutoff frequency (a- or k-rate) 
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>xQ</emphasis> -- filter Q (min 0.5) (a- or k-rate). 
    </para>
       <para>
      <emphasis>kdrive</emphasis> -- overdrive factor. With the
      internal non-linear map, values above
      0.125 will introduce progressively more non-linearities in the
      filter signal. When using a user-supplied transfer function, the
      amount of distortion introduced by this parameter will depend on
      the function employed. A value of 0 makes the filter completely linear.
      The amount of drive is also dependent on the level of the input
      signal. If this signal is significantly less than 0dBFS, then proportionally
      more drive is needed to introduce non-linearities in the
      signal. With a 0dBFS-level input, 100% drive is achieved with
      kdrive=1. With hotter input levels, kdrive can be used to
      moderate the non-linear distortion in the filter.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the svn opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/svn.csd"><citetitle>svn.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the svn opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/svn.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: &namevictor;</member>
        <member>Feb 2021</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry> 
