
<refentry id="tablewa">
<indexterm id="IndexTablewa"><primary>tablewa</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Table Control:Read/Write Operations</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>tablewa</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>tablewa</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Writes tables in sequential locations.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      This opcode writes to a table in sequential locations to and from an a-rate variable. Some thought is required before using it. It has at least two major, and quite different, applications which are discussed below.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>kstart <command>tablewa</command> kfn, asig, koff</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> -- Where in table to read or write.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>kfn</emphasis> -- i- or k-rate number of the table to read or write.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>asig</emphasis> -- a-rate signal to read from when writing to the table.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>koff</emphasis> -- i- or k-rate offset into table. Range unlimited - see explanation at end of this section.
    </para>
 
    <para>
      In one application, it is intended to be used with one or with several <link linkend="tablera"><citetitle>tablera</citetitle></link> opcodes before a <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis> -- all sharing the same <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> variable.
    </para>

    <para>
      These read from and write to sequential locations in a table at audio rates, with <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> floats being written and read each cycle.
    </para>

    <para>
      <link linkend="tablera"><citetitle>tablera</citetitle></link> starts reading from location <emphasis>kstart</emphasis>. <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis> starts writing to location <emphasis>kstart</emphasis>, and then writes to <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> with the number of the location one more than the one it last wrote. (Note that for <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis>, <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> is both an input and output variable.) If the writing index reaches the end of the table, then no further writing occurs and zero is written to <emphasis>kstart</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      For instance, if the table's length was 16 (locations 0 to 15), and <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> was 5. Then the following steps would occur with repetitive runs of the <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis> opcode, assuming that <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> started at 0.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Run Number</entry>
            <entry>Initial kstart</entry>
            <entry>Final kstart</entry>
            <entry>Locations Written</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
 
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>0</entry>
            <entry>5</entry>
            <entry>0 1 2 3 4</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>2</entry>
            <entry>5</entry>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>5 6 7 8 9</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>3</entry>
            <entry>10</entry>
            <entry>15</entry>
            <entry>10 11 12 13 14</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>4</entry>
            <entry>15</entry>
            <entry>0</entry>
            <entry>15</entry>
          </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      This is to facilitate processing table data using standard a-rate orchestra code between the <link linkend="tablera"><citetitle>tablera</citetitle></link> and <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis> opcodes. They allow all Csound k-rate operators to be used (with caution) on a-rate variables - something that would only be possible otherwise by <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> = 1, downsamp and upsamp.
    </para>

    <caution>
      <title>Several cautions</title>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The k-rate code in the processing loop is really running at a-rate, so time dependent functions like <emphasis>port</emphasis> and <emphasis>oscil</emphasis> work faster than normal - their code is expecting to be running at k-rate.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              This system will produce undesirable results unless the <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> fits within the table length. For instance a table of length 16 will accommodate 1 to 16 samples, so this example will work with <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> = 1 to 16.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </caution>

    <para>
      Both these opcodes generate an error and deactivate the instrument if a table with length &lt; <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> is selected. Likewise an error occurs if <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> is below 0 or greater than the highest entry in the table - if <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> = table length.
    </para>

    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> is intended to contain integer values between 0 and (table length - 1). Fractional values above this should not affect operation but do not achieve anything useful.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            These opcodes are not interpolating, and the <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> and <emphasis>koff</emphasis> parameters always have a range of 0 to (table length - 1) - not 0 to 1 as is available in other table read/write opcodes. <emphasis>koff</emphasis> can be outside this range but it is wrapped around by the final AND operation.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            These opcodes are permanently in wrap mode. When <emphasis>koff</emphasis> is 0, no wrapping needs to occur, since the <emphasis>kstart</emphasis>++ index will always be within the table's normal range. <emphasis>koff</emphasis> not equal to  0 can lead to wrapping.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The offset does not affect the number of read/write cycles performed, or the value written to <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> by <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            These opcodes cannot read or write the guardpoint. Use <emphasis>tablegpw</emphasis> to write the guardpoint after manipulations have been done with <emphasis>tablewa</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
     <informalexample>
        <programlisting>
kstart   <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis>       0         
                           
<emphasis role="olabel">lab1:</emphasis>
  atemp  <emphasis role="opc">tablera</emphasis> ktabsource, kstart, 0  <emphasis role="comment">; Read 5 values from table into an</emphasis>
         <emphasis role="comment">; a-rate variable.</emphasis> 
                           
  atemp  <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis>       <emphasis role="opc">log</emphasis>(atemp)  <emphasis role="comment">; Process the values using a-rate</emphasis>
         <emphasis role="comment">; code.</emphasis>    

  kstart <emphasis role="opc">tablewa</emphasis> ktabdest, atemp, 0   <emphasis role="comment">; Write it back to the table</emphasis>
         
<emphasis role="octrl">if</emphasis> ktemp  0 <emphasis role="octrl">goto</emphasis> <emphasis role="olabel">lab1</emphasis>      <emphasis role="comment">; Loop until all table locations</emphasis>
         <emphasis role="comment">; have been processed.</emphasis></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>

    <para>
      The above example shows a processing loop, which runs every k-cycle, reading each location in the table <emphasis>ktabsource</emphasis>, and writing the log of those values into the same locations of table <emphasis>ktabdest</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      This enables whole tables, parts of tables (with offsets and different control loops) and data from several tables at once to be manipulated with a-rate code and written back to another (or to the same) table. This is a bit of a fudge, but it is faster than doing it with k-rate table read and write code.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another application is:
    </para>

    <para>
     <informalexample>
        <programlisting>
kzero <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis> 0                    
kloop <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis> 0                    
                                 
kzero <emphasis role="opc">tablewa</emphasis> 23, asignal, 0  <emphasis role="comment">; ksmps a-rate samples written</emphasis>
       <emphasis role="comment">; into locations 0 to (ksmps -1) of table 23.</emphasis>
                                
<emphasis role="olabel">lab1:</emphasis> ktemp <emphasis role="opc">table</emphasis> kloop, 23  <emphasis role="comment">; Start a loop which runs ksmps times,</emphasis>
       <emphasis role="comment">; in which each cycle processes one of</emphasis>
 [ Some code to manipulate ]  <emphasis role="comment">; table 23's values with k-rate orchestra</emphasis>
 [ the value of ktemp. ]  <emphasis role="comment">; code.</emphasis>
                                 
 <emphasis role="opc">tablew</emphasis> ktemp, kloop, 23  <emphasis role="comment">; Write the processed value to the table.</emphasis>
                                
kloop <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis> kloop <emphasis role="op">+</emphasis> 1      <emphasis role="comment">; Increment the kloop, which is both the</emphasis>
       <emphasis role="comment">; pointer into the table and the loop</emphasis>
<emphasis role="octrl">if</emphasis> kloop <emphasis role="op">&lt;</emphasis> ksmps <emphasis role="octrl">goto</emphasis> <emphasis role="olabel">lab1</emphasis>  <emphasis role="comment">; counter. Keep looping until all values</emphasis>
       <emphasis role="comment">; in the table have been processed.</emphasis>
                                
asignal   <emphasis role="opc">tablera</emphasis> 23, 0, 0  <emphasis role="comment">; Copy the table contents back</emphasis>
       <emphasis role="comment">; to an a-rate variable.</emphasis></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>koff</emphasis> -- This is an offset which is added to the sum of <emphasis>kstart</emphasis> and the internal index variable which steps through the table. The result is then ANDed with the lengthmask (000 0111 for a table of length 8 - or 9 with guardpoint) and that final index is used to read or write to the table. <emphasis>koff</emphasis> can be any value. It is converted into a long using the ANSI floor() function so that -4.3 becomes -5. This is what we would want when using offsets which range above and below zero.
    </para>

    <para>
      Ideally this would be an optional variable, defaulting to 0, however with the existing Csound orchestra read code, such default parameters must be init time only. We want k-rate here, so we cannot have a default.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: Robin Whittle</member>
        <member>Australia</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
