
<refentry id="timedseq">
<indexterm id="IndexTimedSeq"><primary>timedseq</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Instrument Control:Sensing and Control</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>timedseq</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>timedseq</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Time Variant Sequencer
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
    An event-sequencer in which time can be controlled by a
    time-pointer. Sequence data are stored into a table.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
      <synopsis>ktrig  <command>timedseq</command>  ktimpnt, ifn, kp1 [,kp2, kp3, ...,kpN]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
    <emphasis>ifn</emphasis> -- number of table containing sequence
    data.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
    <emphasis>ktri</emphasis> -- output trigger signal
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>ktimpnt</emphasis> -- time pointer into sequence file, in seconds.
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>kp1,...,kpN</emphasis> -- output p-fields of notes. kp2
    meaning is relative action time and kp3 is the duration of notes
    in seconds.
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>timedseq</emphasis> is a sequencer that allows to schedule
    notes starting from a user sequence, and depending from an external
    timing given by a time-pointer value (ktimpnt argument). User should
    fill table ifn with a list of notes, that can be provided in an
    external text file by using GEN23, or by typing it directly in the
    orchestra (or score) file with GEN02. The format of the text file
    containing the sequence is made up simply by rows containing several
    numbers separated by space (similarly to normal Csound score).  The
    first value of each row must be a positive or null value, except for a
    special case that will be explained below. This first value is
    normally used to define the instrument number corresponding to that
    particular note (like normal score). The second value of each row must
    contain the action time of corresponding note and the third value its
    duration. This is an example:
  </para>
<programlisting>
0 0    0.25 1  93
0 0.25 0.25 2  63
0 0.5  0.25 3  91
0 0.75 0.25 4  70
0 1    0.25 5  83
0 1.25 0.25 6  75
0 1.5  0.25 7  78
0 1.75 0.25 8  78
0 2    0.25 9  83
0 2.25 0.25 10 70
0 2.5  0.25 11 54
0 2.75 0.25 12 80
-1 3   -1   -1 -1  ;; last row of the sequence
</programlisting>
  <para>
    In this example, the first value of each row is always zero (it is a
    dummy value, but this p-field can be used, for example, to express a
    MIDI channel or an instrument number), except the last row, that
    begins with -1. This value (-1) is a special value, that indicates the
    end of sequence. It has itself an action time, because sequences can be
    looped. So the previous sequence has a default duration of 3 seconds,
    being value 3 the last action time of the sequence.
  </para>
  <para>
    It is important that ALL lines contains the same number of values (in
    the example all rows contains exactly 5 values). The number of values
    contained by each row, MUST be the number of kpXX output arguments
    (notice that, even if kp1, kp2 etc. are placed at the right of the
    opcode, they are output arguments, not input arguments).
  </para>
  <para>
    ktimpnt argument provide the real temporization of the
    sequence. Actually the passage of time through sequence is specified
    by ktimpnt itself, which represents the time in seconds. ktimpnt must
    always be positive, but can move forwards or backwards in time, be
    stationary or discontinuous, as a pointer into the sequence file, in
    the same way of pvoc or lpread. When ktimpnt crosses the action time
    of a note, a trigger signal is sent to ktrig output argument, and kp1,
    kp2,...kpN arguments are updated with the values of that note. This
    information can then be used with schedkwhen to actually
    activate note events. Notice that kp1,...kpn data can be further
    processed (for example delayed with delayk, transposed, etc.) before
    feeding schedkwhen.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>ktimpnt</emphasis> can be controlled by a linear signal, for example:
  </para>
<programlisting>
ktimpnt <emphasis role="opc">line</emphasis>     0, p3, 3  <emphasis role="comment">; original sequence duration was 3 secs</emphasis>
ktrig   <emphasis role="opc">timedseq</emphasis> ktimpnt, 1, kp1, kp2, kp3, kp4, kp5
        <emphasis role="opc">schedkwhen</emphasis>   ktrig, 105, 2, 0, kp3, kp4, kp5</programlisting>
  <para>
    in this case the complete sequence (with original duration of 3
    seconds) will be played in <emphasis>p3</emphasis> seconds.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can loop a sequence by controlling it with a phasor:
<programlisting>
kphs    <emphasis role="opc">phasor</emphasis>   1<emphasis role="op">/</emphasis>3
ktimpnt <emphasis role="op">=</emphasis>        kphs <emphasis role="op">*</emphasis> 3
ktrig   <emphasis role="opc">timedseq</emphasis> ktimpnt ,1 ,kp1, kp2, kp3, kp4, kp5
        <emphasis role="opc">schedkwhen</emphasis>   ktrig, 105, 2, 0, kp3, kp4, kp5</programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
  Obviously you can play only a fragment of the sequence,  read it
  backward, and non-linearly access sequence data in the same way of
  pvoc and lpread opcodes.
  </para>
  <para>
  With timedseq opcode you can do almost all things of a normal score,
  except you have the following limitations:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You cannot have two notes exactly starting with the same action
        time; actually at least a k-cycle should separate timing of two
        notes (otherwise the schedkwhen mechanism eats one of them).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All notes of the sequence must have the same number of p-fields
        (even if they activate different instruments).</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    You can remedy this limitation by filling with dummy values notes that belongs to
    instruments with less p-fields than other ones.
  </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is a complete example of the timedseq opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/timedseq.csd"><citetitle>timedseq.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>Example of the timedseq opcode.</title>
        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/timedseq.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="GEN02"><citetitle>GEN02</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="GEN23"><citetitle>GEN23</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="seqtime"><citetitle>seqtime</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="seqtime"><citetitle>seqtime2</citetitle></link>,
      <link linkend="trigseq"><citetitle>trigseq</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      Author: &namegabriel;
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
