
<refentry id="websocket">
<indexterm id="IndexWebsocket"><primary>websocket</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Signal I/O:File I/O</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>websocket</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>websocket</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Read and write signals and arrays using a websocket connection.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>Plugin opcode in websocketIO.</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>websocket</emphasis> reads and writes <emphasis>N</emphasis> signals and arrays using a websocket connection.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>xout1[, xout2, xout3, ..., xoutN] <command>websocket</command> iport, xin</synopsis>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
        <emphasis>iport</emphasis> the local web port to read/write data.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>xout1,... xoutN</emphasis> -- The output variables
      which contain data received from a websocket. On the web side
      the websocket must send data using a protocol name that matches
      the output variable name e.g. "ksignal" for a k-rate
      variable. If an array is intended to be received from a
      websocket it must be first initialised before being used as an
      output to the opcode. Otherwise the opcode does not know what size data to expect from the websocket. When sending data to a websocket from the web page it must be sent as a 32 or 64 bit array, depending on the build of Csound that is being used. 
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>xin</emphasis> -- The input variable
        which contains data to be sent to a websocket. On the web
        side the websocket receives data using a protocol name that
        matches the input variable name e.g. "ksignal" for a k-rate
        variable. When receiving data from a websocket on the web page
        it must be read as a 32 or 64 bit array, depending on the
        build of Csound that is being used. <note>The total number of
        input and output arguments is limited to 20.</note>
    </para>

    <title>Data Formatting</title>
    <para> 
        A-rate variables must be send and received as arrays that are <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> samples large. A-rate arrays similarly are sent and received as <emphasis>ksmps</emphasis> by the number of elements in the array. K-rate variables are sent and received as a single element array. K-rate arrays are sent and received as arrays with matching numbers of elements. 
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is a simple example of the websocket opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/websocket.csd"><citetitle>websocket.csd</citetitle></ulink> and <ulink url="examples/websocket.html"><citetitle>websocket.html</citetitle></ulink>.

      <example>
        <title>Example of the websocket opcode.</title>

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/websocket.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>
    </para>

</refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para>
      <link linkend="OSClisten"><citetitle>OSClisten</citetitle></link>
      <link linkend="OSCsend"><citetitle>OSCsend</citetitle></link>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Author: Edward Costello;</member>
        <member>NUIM, 2015</member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <para>New in version 6.06</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
