<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" id="xyin">
<indexterm id="IndexXyin"><primary>xyin</primary></indexterm>
  <refentryinfo><title>Instrument Control:Sensing and Control</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>xyin</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>


 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>xyin</refname>

    <refpurpose>
      Sense the cursor position in an output window
          </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Sense the cursor position in an output window. When <emphasis>xyin</emphasis> is called the position of the mouse within the output window is used to reply to the request.  This simple mechanism does mean that only one <emphasis>xyin</emphasis> can be used accurately at once.  The position of the mouse is reported in the output window.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis>kx, ky <command>xyin</command> iprd, ixmin, ixmax, iymin, iymax [, ixinit] [, iyinit]</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>iprd</emphasis> -- period of cursor sensing (in seconds). Typically .1 seconds.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>xmin, xmax, ymin, ymax</emphasis> -- edge values for the x-y coordinates of a cursor in the input window.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>ixinit, iyinit</emphasis> (optional) -- initial x-y coordinates reported; the default values are 0,0. If these values are not within the given min-max range, they will be coerced into that range.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>xyin</emphasis> samples the cursor x-y position in an input window every <emphasis>iprd</emphasis> seconds. Output values are repeated (not interpolated) at the k-rate, and remain fixed until a new change is registered in the window. There may be any number of input windows. This unit is useful for real-time control, but continuous motion should be avoided if <emphasis>iprd</emphasis> is unusually small.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Depending on your platform and distribution, you might need to enable displays using the <emphasis>--displays</emphasis> command line flag.
      </para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the xyin opcode. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/xyin.csd"><citetitle>xyin.csd</citetitle></ulink>.

      <example>
        <title>Example of the xyin opcode.</title>

        

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples-xml/xyin.csd.xml"/>
      </example>

      As the values of kx and ky change, they will be printed out like this:
      <screen>
kx=8.612036, ky=22.677933
kx=10.765685, ky=15.644135
      </screen>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Example written by Kevin Conder.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
