
<refentry id="GEN05">
      <indexterm id="IndexGEN05"><primary>GEN05</primary></indexterm>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>GEN05</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>GEN05</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Constructs functions from segments of exponential curves.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      Constructs functions from segments of exponential curves.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis><command>f</command> # time size 5 a n1 b n2 c ...</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>size </emphasis> -- number of points in the table. Must be a power of 2 or power-of-2 plus 1 (see <link linkend="f"><citetitle>f statement</citetitle></link>).
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>a, b, c,</emphasis> etc. -- ordinate values, in odd-numbered pfields p5, p7, p9, . . . These must be nonzero and must be alike in sign.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>n1, n2</emphasis>, etc. -- length of segment (no. of
      storage locations), in even-numbered pfields. Cannot be
      negative, but a zero is meaningful for specifying discontinuous
      waveforms. The sum <emphasis>n1</emphasis> +
      <emphasis>n2</emphasis> + .... will normally equal
      <emphasis>size</emphasis> for fully specified functions. If the
      sum is smaller, the function locations not included will be set
      to zero; if the sum is greater, only the first
      <emphasis>size</emphasis> locations will be stored.  Note that
      the values are rounded to integers before use.
    </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If p4 is positive, functions are post-normalized (rescaled to a maximum absolute value of 1 after generation). A negative p4 will cause rescaling to be skipped.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Discrete-point linear interpolation implies an increase or decrease along a segment by equal differences between adjacent locations; exponential interpolation implies that the progression is by equal ratio. In both forms the interpolation from <emphasis>a</emphasis> to <emphasis>b</emphasis> is such as to assume that the value <emphasis>b</emphasis> will be attained in the n + 1th location. For discontinuous functions, and for the segment encompassing the end location, this value will not actually be reached, although it may eventually appear as a result of final scaling.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      Here is a simple example of the GEN05 routine. It uses the files <ulink url="examples/gen05.csd"><citetitle>gen05.csd</citetitle></ulink>.
      <example>
        <title>An example of the GEN05 routine.</title>
        <xi:include href="examples-xml/gen05.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </example>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>These are the diagrams of the waveforms of the GEN05 routines, as used in the example:</phrase>
        </textobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gen05_1.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>f 2 0 129 5 1 100 0.0001 29 - waveform that goes over 100 points from 1 to 0.0001, stay there for 29 points</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>f 2 0 129 5 1 100 0.0001 29 - waveform that goes over 100 points from 1 to 0.0001, stay there for 29 points</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gen05_2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>f 3 0 129 5 0.00001 87 1 22 .5 20 0.0001 - waveform that goes from 0.00001 to 1 in 87 points, then from 1 to .5 in 22 points and then from .5 to 0.0001 in 20 points</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>f 3 0 129 5 0.00001 87 1 22 .5 20 0.0001 - waveform that goes from 0.00001 to 1 in 87 points, then from 1 to .5 in 22 points and then from .5 to 0.0001 in 20 points</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
     <title>See Also</title>
     <para>
       <link linkend="GEN06"><citetitle>GEN06</citetitle></link>,
       <link linkend="GEN07"><citetitle>GEN07</citetitle></link>, and
       <link linkend="GEN08"><citetitle>GEN08</citetitle></link>
     </para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
