
<chapter id="MidiTop">
  <title>Real-time MIDI Support</title>
  <para>
    Csound supports realtime MIDI input and output, as well as input
    from MIDI files. Realtime MIDI input is activated using the <link
    linkend="FlagsCatMinusUpperM"><citetitle>-M</citetitle></link> (or
    <emphasis>--midi-device</emphasis>=DEVICE) command line flag. For
    single port input, you
    must specify the device number or name after the
    <emphasis>-M</emphasis>. For multiport input (currently
    implemented only in the PortMIDI module),  use 'a' or 'm'.
    For example to use device number 2, you would use something like:
  </para>
  <literallayout>csound -M2 myrtmidi.csd</literallayout>
  <para>
    You can find out the available devices by running Csound with
    --midi-devices option:
  </para>
  <literallayout>csound --midi-devices</literallayout>
 
<para>
Starting from version 6.14, the PortMIDI module (see below for a list
of all modules) allows multiple ports to be mapped to higher-order
channels. By using the 'm' device name, Csound will take inputs from
any existing MIDI device in the system and map it according to
(N+1)*channel, where N is the device number as listed by PortMIDI and
channel is the original device input channel. Alternatively, the 'a'
device name listens to all inputs but does not map to higher-order
channels.
</para>

  <para>
    Realtime MIDI output is activated using <link linkend="FlagsCatMinusUpperQ"><citetitle>-Q</citetitle></link>, using device number or names as shown above.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can also load a MIDI file using the <link linkend="FlagsCatMinusUpperF"><citetitle>-F</citetitle></link> or <emphasis>--midifile</emphasis>=FILE command line flag. The MIDI file is read in realtime, and behaves as if it was being performed or received in realtime. So the csound program is not aware if MIDI input comes from a MIDI file or directly from a MIDI interface.
  </para>
  <para>
    Once realtime MIDI input and/or output has been activated, opcodes like <link linkend="MidiInput"><citetitle>MIDI Input</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="MidiOutput"><citetitle>MIDI Output</citetitle></link> will have effect.
  </para>  <para>
    When MIDI input is enabled (with -M or -F), each incoming <emphasis>noteon</emphasis> message will generate a note event for an instrument which has the same number as the channel of the event  (This means that MIDI controlled instruments are polyphonic by default, since each note will generate a new instance of the instrument.)
If you have 1 instrument only, Csound works in omni mode, ie. it responds to all channels into that single instrument.
If you have more than one instrument and instrs 1 - 16 , then by default  instr 1 -> chn 1, instr 2 -> chn 2, unless you alter the mapping (see <link linkend="massign"><citetitle>massign</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="pgmassign"><citetitle>pgmassign</citetitle></link> to change this behavior).
For a single port input, if you have more than one instrument, but instr N in between 1 - 16 is missing, then chn N will be routed by default to the lowest order instrument.
  </para>
  <para>
    See the <link linkend="MidiInterop"><citetitle>MIDI/Score Interoperability</citetitle></link> opcodes for information on designing instruments which can be used from the score or driven by MIDI.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are several realtime MIDI modules available, you must use the <emphasis>-+rtmidi</emphasis> flag (See <link linkend="FlagsCatMinusPlusRtmidi"><citetitle>-+rtmidi</citetitle></link>), to specify the module. The default module is portmidi which provides adequate MIDI I/O on all platforms, however for improved performance and reliability some platform specific modules are also provided.
  </para>
  <para>
    Currently the midi modules available are:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>portmidi</emphasis> - To use the
      PortMIDI system (all platforms). This is the default setting and
      it allows multiple-port inputs (with 'm' or 'a' device names).</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>alsa</emphasis> - To use the ALSA midi system (Linux only)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>jack</emphasis> - To use the Jack midi system</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>winmme</emphasis> - To use the windows MME system (Windows only)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>virtual</emphasis> - To use a virtual graphical keyboard (See below) as MIDI input (all platforms)</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <tip>
    <para>When csound runs, it will process the score and then
    quit. If there are no events in the score, Csound will run
    forever. If you want to use only MIDI events instead of score
    events and you know how long you wish t run, you can tell Csound
    to run that amount of time by using the dummy <link linkend="f"><citetitle>f-statement</citetitle></link> like "f 0 360".
    </para>
  </tip>

  &midivirtual;
  &midiinput;
  &midioutput;
  &midigeneric;
  &midiconvert;
  &midiextender;
  &midionoff;
  &midiinterop;
  &midirealtime;
  &midisliderbk;

</chapter>
