
<refentry id="lpanal">
  <refentryinfo><title>Utilities</title></refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>lpanal</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
 
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>lpanal</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Performs both linear predictive and pitch-tracking analysis on a soundfile.
      <indexterm id="IndexLpanal"><primary>lpanal</primary></indexterm>
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
	    Linear predictive analysis for the Csound <link linkend="SpectralLpcresyn"><citetitle>Linear Predictive Coding (LPC) Resynthesis</citetitle></link> opcodes. 
    </para>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Syntax</title>
    <synopsis><command>csound -U lpanal</command> [flags] infilename outfilename</synopsis>

    <synopsis><command>lpanal</command> [flags] infilename outfilename</synopsis>
  </refsect1>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Initialization</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>lpanal</emphasis> performs both lpc and pitch-tracking analysis on a soundfile to produce a time-ordered sequence of <emphasis>frames</emphasis> of control information suitable for Csound resynthesis. Analysis is conditioned by the control flags below. A space is optional between the flag and its value.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-a</emphasis> -- [alternate storage] asks lpanal to write a file with filter poles values rather than the usual filter coefficient files. When <emphasis>lpread</emphasis> / <emphasis>lpreson</emphasis> are used with pole files, automatic stabilization is performed and the filter should not get wild. (This is the default in the Windows GUI) - Changed by Marc Resibois.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-s srate</emphasis> -- sampling rate of the audio input file. This will over-ride the srate of the soundfile header, which otherwise applies. If neither is present, the default is 10000.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-c channel</emphasis> -- channel number sought. The default is 1.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-b begin</emphasis> -- beginning time (in seconds) of the audio segment to be analyzed. The default is 0.0
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-d duration</emphasis> -- duration (in seconds) of the audio segment to be analyzed. The default of 0.0 means to the end of the file.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-p npoles</emphasis> -- number of poles for analysis. The default is 34, the maximum 50.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-h hopsize</emphasis> -- hop size (in samples) between frames of analysis. This determines the number of frames per second (srate / hopsize) in the output control file. The analysis framesize is hopsize * 2 samples. The default is 200, the maximum 500.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-C string</emphasis> -- text for the comments field of the lpfile header. The default is the null string.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-P mincps</emphasis> -- lowest frequency (in Hz) of pitch tracking. -P0 means no pitch tracking.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-Q maxcps</emphasis> -- highest frequency (in Hz) of pitch tracking. The narrower the pitch range, the more accurate the pitch estimate. The defaults are -P70, -Q200.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-v verbosity</emphasis> -- level of terminal information during analysis. 
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>0 = none</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>1 = verbose</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>2 = debug</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      The default is 0.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>-X</emphasis> -- write machine independent format
      analysis file.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
	
    <refsect2>
      <title>File Format </title>
      <para>
        Output is a file comprised of an identifiable header plus a set of frames of floating point analysis data. Each frame contains four values of pitch and gain information, followed by <emphasis>npoles</emphasis> filter coefficients. The file is readable by Csound's <link linkend="lpread"><citetitle>lpread</citetitle></link>.
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>lpanal</emphasis> is an extensive modification of Paul Lanksy's lpc analysis programs.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
 
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>
<!--       <informalexample> -->
        <programlisting>
<emphasis>lpanal</emphasis> -a -p26 -d2.5 -P100 -Q400 audiofile.test lpfil22</programlisting>
<!--       </informalexample> -->

      will analyze the first 2.5 seconds of file &quot;audiofile.test&quot;, producing srate/200 frames per second, each containing 26-pole filter coefficients and a pitch estimate between 100 and 400 Hertz. Stabilized (<emphasis>-a</emphasis>) output will be placed in &quot;lpfil22&quot; in the current directory.
    </para>
    <para>
      Here is an example of the lpanal utility. It uses the file <ulink url="examples/lpanal.csd"><citetitle>lpanal.csd</citetitle></ulink>.

      <example>
        <title>Example of the lpanal utility.</title>

        <para>See the sections <link linkend="UsingRealTime"><citetitle>Real-time Audio</citetitle></link> and <link linkend="CommandFlags"><citetitle>Command Line Flags</citetitle></link> for more information on using command line flags.</para>
          <xi:include href="examples-xml/lpanal.csd.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

      </example>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
