
<chapter id="Configuring">

  <title>Configuring</title>
  <para>Once you have either unpacked a binary distribution, or built
    Csound from sources, you will need to configure Csound so that it will run properly on your system. Installers usually perform these steps for you automatically.
  </para>
  <para>On all platforms, make sure the directory or directories
  containing Csound's plugin libraries are in an
  <literal>OPCODE6DIR</literal> or <literal>OPCODE6DIR64</literal>
  environment variable depending on the precision of the compiled
  binary.
  (Note that for csound5 these environment variables were
  <literal>OPCODE6DIR</literal> and <literal>OPCODE6DIR64</literal>.)
  </para>
  <para>The Python opcodes currently require at least Python 2.4, which can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://www.python.org">www.python.org</ulink> if it is not already on your system. You can check if it is available by typing 'python' on a command prompt or DOS window.
  </para>
  <bridgehead>Windows</bridgehead>
    <para>On Windows, make sure the directory or directories (normally the <filename>C:\Program Files\Csound</filename> directory) containing the Csound executables directory are in your <literal>PATH</literal> variable, or else copy all the executable files to your Windows <filename>system32</filename> directory. Depending on your installation method, you might also need to set the <literal>OPCODEDIR</literal> and <literal>OPCODEDIR64</literal> environment variables. Assuming that Csound is installed to the default location of <filename>C:\Program Files\Csound</filename> you can use (otherwise set the paths accordingly):
    </para>
  <screen>set OPCODEDIR=C:\Program Files\Csound\plugins
set OPCODEDIR64=C:\Program Files\Csound\plugins64
set PATH=%PATH%;C:\Program Files\Csound\bin</screen>

  <note>
    <title>Missing python24.dll or python25.dll</title>
    <para>If you get a pop-up about the missing Python library (python24.dll or python25.dll) and don't need the python opcodes, just delete <filename>C:\Program Files\Csound\plugins\py.dll</filename> and <filename>C:\Program Files\Csound\plugins64\py.dll</filename>, and the pop-up about the missing Python library should be gone.</para>
  </note>
  <bridgehead>Unix and Linux</bridgehead>
  <para>On Unix and Linux, either install the Csound program in one of the system <filename>bin</filename> directories, typically <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>, and the Csound and plugin shared libraries in places like <filename>/usr/local/lib/csound/plugins</filename> or <filename>/usr/local/lib/csound/plugins64</filename> and make sure that <literal>OPCODEDIR</literal> and <literal>OPCODEDIR64</literal> environment variable are set correctly.
  </para>

  <bridgehead>CsoundAC</bridgehead>

    <para>CsoundAC requires some additional configuration. On all
      platforms, CsoundAC requires that you have Python installed on your
      computer. The directory containing the <filename>_csoundAC</filename> shared
      library and the <filename>CsoundAC.py</filename> file must be in your
      <literal>PYTHONPATH</literal> environment variable, so that the Python runtime
      knows how to load these files.</para>

</chapter>
